Guide to the Max Black papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
Black, Max papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Max Black papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
14-21-2466
Max Black, 1909-
32.0 cubic ft.
Correspondence, files, and a manuscript.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Professional papers include correspondence, subject files, and files relating to his work with the Science, Technology, and Society program at Cornell. Also, manuscript of Black's book Rational Choice, the Prisoner's Dilemma.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Philosopher, Professor of Philosophy at Cornell University.
Max Black received two doctoral degrees from the University of London. He taught at the University of London from 1936 to 1940 and at the University of Illinois from 1940 to 1946. He joined the faculty at Cornell in 1946, becoming the Susan Linn Sage Professor of Philosophy in 1954. In 1965, Black became the first director of Cornell's Society for the Humanities, a position he held until 1971. Since 1971, he was a member of the Cornell program on Science, Technology and Society and academic head of its Unit on Humanities, Science and Technology. His first publication was a discussion of Jeremy Bentham's theory of definition. He has written numerous works on philosophical subjects, including books on mathematics, Wittgenstein, and the nature of the university.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Professional papers include correspondence, subject files, and files relating to his work with the Science, Technology, and Society program at Cornell. Also, manuscript of Black's book Rational Choice, the Prisoner's Dilemma.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Black, Max, 1909-1988; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Philosophy--Study and teaching.; Philosophers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 31 and 32 are restricted to permission of donor.
CONTAINER LIST
- Probability; Induction; Mss. (Past); Cornell University matters; Fellowships & Grants; Lectures; Publications, Society for Humanities, 1940s-[1960s] (Box 1)
- Papers; Testimonials; reprints of his ritings, 1940s-[ ] (Box 2)
- Course files; Paper on Necessity; Alphabetical file A-Z; Notes A-P on various philosophical subjects (Box 3)
- Notes P-W on various philosophical subjects; Tractatus by Wittgenstein (notes and papers) (Box 4)
- Wittgenstein continued; Writing Projects (notes, course notes, arranged alphabetically A-S); Social Science (course notes, reprints, etc.) (Box 5)
- Course work, notes, drafts, papers, reprints on philosophical topics, 1928-[1950s-1960s] (Box 6)
- Course work for systematics; Philosophy of Science course material; India (1962); Japan (1957); Philosophy of Education, [1960s] (Box 7)
- Reprints by others; Topics (notes and papers); Seminars (Past); Tarners Lecture, [1960s]-1978 (Box 8)
- Logic, [1950s-1960s] (Box 9)
- Course material; Academic; reprints, [1960s] (Box 10)
- Bound typescript copies of papers by others; Logical Possibility by M.B. (bd. typsc.) - 2 cassettes (Box 11)
- Alphabetical Subject Files; Misc. I & J, Knowledge, Language, Literary Criticism, Logic, Measurement, Metaphors, Moore and "O", [1970s-1980s] (Box 12)
- Subject Files continued, O-R: Observation, Paradoxes, Philosophy, Practical Reasoning, Probability, Rationality, Reasonable Rules, Russell, [1970s] (Box 13)
- Subject Files continued, S-W: Scholarly Responsibility, Sets, Should and Is, Technion Papers, Technology, University (Open), Verifiability, [1970s] (Box 14)
- Wittgenstein continued; Misc. in separate drawer, incl. Lord Ashby, Humbug, [1970s] (Box 15)
- Professional alpha file A-W incls i.e. C.U. Adult Univ.; Financial, [1970s-1980s] (Box 16)
- Professional alphabetical files I-W; Trips (old), [1970s-1980s] (Box 17)
- Subject files; reprints of M. Black; India, [1970s-1980s] (Box 18)
- Typescripts Memoir of M.B. (Rosenbaum, interviewer); cassettes of lectures; notes (Box 19)
- Notes on philosophical subjects: incl. Tarners Lecture series, [1960s-1970s] (Box 20)
- Philosophical files incl. Tarners Lecture, [1970s-1980s] (Box 21)
- Alpha file: M-Skepticism, Science, Spare, "P"; course material, [1970s] (Box 22)
- Course material; Other Papers; Dromoland Papers, 1972, [1970s] (Box 23)
- Course material; notes and papers, [1960s] (Box 24)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence A-D, [1970s]-1980s (Box 25)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence E-L, [1970s] (Box 26)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence L-R, [1970s] (Box 27)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence S-Z, [1970s] (Box 28)
- Subject files, A-I: Aspen Colloquium, Communication; Determinism; Explanation; Goodman; Humanism; Humanities, Induction, [1970s] (Box 29)
- Humanities Science and Technology - Rockefeller Foundation, Correspondence and Proposals, Annual Reports, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Humanities Science and Technology - Annual Reports, Colloquia, Workshops, [1970s] (Box 30)
- NEH and NSF - Proposals, Grants and Correspondence, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Publications, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Max Black's Memoir, including original tape recordings from oral interview, 1987 (Box 30)
- Letters to Rosenbaum and Naomi Black, 1961-1987 (Box 31)
- Letters to Michael, 1931-1972 (Box 31)
- Diaries (Box 31)
- Family photographs, diaries (Box 32)